（希腊 桑托里尼）
《古墓丽影：生命之匙》
他们又找到一个
They found another one.
等到她来宝藏早就没了
There's going to be no treasure left by the time she gets here!
标示位置
Mark the location!
那是法国佬，克里斯多也来了
That's the Frenchman!And over there, Kristos.
全都到齐了，只差一个人
They're all coming.All except one.
好，跟着克里斯多
All right, follow Kristos.
他潜水，我们也下去
When he dives, we dive.
走运的话
Maybe we'll get lucky
也许会找到宝藏
and find whatever it is that's down there.
你快看，吉米
Hey, look at that, Jimmy. Look.
她怎么不减速？
Why isn't she slowing down?
- 你问我吗？- 我就知道
- You were asking? - I knew it.
噢！
Whoa!
两位，你们全湿透了
Hello, boys. You're all wet.
很多盗墓者都来了
Half the world's raiders are already here,
你居然姗姗来迟
and you make us wait.
你也知道我就爱找乐子
But you know I can't resist a bit of fun.
嗯
Huh.
劳拉 这是怎么回事？
Lara, tell us, what's all this fuss about?
他们认为下面有什么？
What does everybody think is down there?
我不知道别人怎么想
Well, I don't kno wwhat everybody thinks is down there
但我认为是月神殿
but… I think it's the Luna Temple.
月神殿？
The Luna Temple?
如果电视没报导
My sons-if it's not on television,
别傻了
forget it.
它是亚历山大大帝盖的
It's a temple built by Alexander the Great.
顺便告诉你，他是希腊人
Who was Greek, in case you don't know.
是的 是的
Yeah, yeah.
亚历山大搜刮全世界的宝藏
Alexander collected treasures from all over the world
然后放在两个地方
He stored them in two places.
大部分放在他埃及的藏宝室
The majority went to his library in Egypt,
但是最珍贵的却在这儿…月神殿
but his most prized possessions went here…the Luna Temple.
他不准任何人记录地点
By law, no one was allowed to record its location.
在西元前330年…
And in 330 B.C. it was…
月神殿沉入大海
…swallowed by the sea.
毁于火山爆发
Destroyed during a volcanic eruption.
永远消失
Lost forever.
直到昨天
Until yesterday.
就算只剩半座神殿
If even half the temple
也是金字塔后最伟大的发现
is intact, it will still be the greatest find since the pyramids.
其他人沿这片陆棚前进
The others heal into this area here along this shelf.
- 根据海流资料？- 没错
- And that's based on the currents? - Yes.
葛斯，我是为了这个才迟到
Ah. This, Gus, was why I was late.
哦
Oh.
这是地震两小时后的地形图
It's a geological, taken two hours after the quake.
震央在这儿，东北方五里
The epicenter was here five miles northeast of us.
但是…你们看现在的海流方向
But look at the currents along the shelf now.
慢着，海流改变方向了
Wait. They've shifted.
所以他们在那儿潜水，遗址其实在…
So, while they're all diving there, the ruins will actually be…
这儿
Here.
动手吧
Let's go.
怎么了？
Something wrong?
亚历山大并未记载神殿的位置
First, Alexander doesn't record the temple's location.
然后上帝用火山爆发将它沉入大海
Then God wipes it from the Earth with a volcano.
现在连海流都改变方向
Now even the currents change.
劳拉，也许月神殿不该被发现
Lara, maybe this temple's not meant to be found.
消失的东西都该被发掘
Everything lost is meant to be found.
放心啦
Don't worry.
好壮观
It's incredible!
真是不可思议
It's unbelievable!
噢
Whoo!
我的天
Oh, my God.
好大的神殿
This is huge.
谢谢
Thanks you
太棒了
Wonderful.
吉米，棒透了
Jimmy, this is wonderful.
你看到了吗？
Do you see what I see?
我的天
Oh, my God.
- 我的天 - 太惊人了
- Oh, my God. - It's incredible.
尼克，你看，我们发大财了
Nicky, look at this. We're going to be rich.
劳拉，你有什么话要对两个帅哥同伴说吗？
Hey, Lara, what do you say to two handsome Greek partners?
等你找到再告诉我
Well, when you find two, let me know.
- 她要你去找 - 不，是你
- Hey, she's talking about you. - No, you.
把金币装起来
Pack the gold coins.
给我那个，给我那个
Give me that.Give me that.
- 劳拉，那是什么？ - 是我的
- Lara, what is that? - It's mine.
她想干嘛？
What is she doing?
劳拉，那根柱子要垮了
Lara, that column is collapsing!
是余震
Aftershock!
- 我们该走了 - 再等两分钟
- I think that'sa sign to leave! - Two minutes.
劳拉 我们必须离开这！
Lara, we need to leave now!
我们该走了
We've got to move!
继续装，这地方要垮了
Keep packing.This thing is gonna collapse!
你拿这两袋
You take those two.
我们要快点 动作快
We have to hurry up!
快点走 快点走 快
We've got to go.We've got to go now! Come on!
好的
Okay.
劳拉
Lara!
劳拉，是我们，
Lara!Lara, it's us.
希拉瑞和布莱斯
Hillary and Bryce!
她漂流了三天，头脑不清楚是很正常
She's disorientated.That's normal after three days.
泡泡水不错吧
Nice day for a dip?
各位，有句话说得好
Gentlemen…there is an expression:
利用大自然会遭到天谴
"It's not nice to fool Mother Nature."
但是我一直在利用大自然
Yet that is preciselywhat I've been doing for some time now.
无论是替孙先生制造沙林毒气
Whether it be sarin gas for Mr. San…
替克先生改良伤寒杆菌…用于巴尔干半岛
improved typhoid or Mr. Krev to use in the Balkans…
也替杜先生增强霍乱的威力
enhanced cholera for Mr. Duvalier.
但是
But…
虽然这些生化武器很有用
while these weapons serve their purpose,
但是始终有极限
there have always been limitations.
一般疾病不能致命
Stable diseases aren't lethal.
致命的疾病却无法持久
Deadly ones burn out too quickly.
大自然的利用价值有限
Mother Nature can only be fooled so much.
但使用我的武器，再强大的敌人也会很快暴毙
Deploy my weapon, and your enemies, however great, will collapse from within.
就像孟沙先生快要暴毙一样
Rather like Mr. Monza is collapsing right now.
这是怎么回事？
What the hell is going on?
孟沙向英国情报局告密
Monza told Ml6 about this meeting.
所以我才更改地点
That's why the change of location.
他打算出卖我，然后向西方寻求政治庇护
He was going to turn me over to them and then seek asylum in the West.
聪明人早该知道我识破阴谋了
A smart man would have known I was on to him.
他不该坐上飞机
He would never have got on the plane.
但是我知道你会，孟沙先生
But I knew you would, Mr. Monza,
因为你以为骗得了我
because you actually thought you could fool me.
各位，这就是叛徒的下场
That, gentlemen, is the sound of a traitor dying.
那是世上最致命的…加速型伊波拉病毒
That was an accelerated form of Ebola, deadliest disease known to man.
传染性很高
Highly contagious.
但是…就像所有的疾病
However…as with all known diseases,
西方囤积了大批抗毒血清
there exist stockpiles of antiserum in the West.
我要卖给你们的病毒，没有抗毒血清
There is no antiserum for what I am offering you.
没有治疗方法、疫苗或解药
No treatment.No vaccine, no cure.
世人从没见过我发掘的东西
The modern world has never seen anything like what I've uncovered.
发掘？
"Uncovered"?
没错，我的事业扩展到…
Yes, I've branched out.
考古学
Archaeology.
0-7-7-4-4
Zero-Seven-Seven-Four-Four
6-8-1
Six-Eight-One.
那是西德意志银行在瑞士分行的帐号
That is the account at the largest bank in Bern.
请你们每人付一亿美元
$100 million each, if you please.
（香港 柴湾私人机场）
陈骆呢？
Where's Chen Lo?
他拿到球，但情报局盯上了他
He's got the orb, but Ml6 is on to him.
- 怎么会被盯上？ - 他也不知道
- How? - He doesn't know,
他不肯冒险送过来，他在等机会
but rather than risk bringing it here, he's waiting.
我已告诉客户潘朵拉魔盒的事，
l have just told a cabin full of men about Pandora.
不能拖延进度
The clock cannot be reset.
叫他立刻把圆球送来给我
Tell Chen Lo to bring the orb to me at once.
你会找到凶手的，别拿我出气
You'll find the killers!Don't take it out on me!
啊
Ya!
布莱斯，怎么样？
Bryce! What have we got?
我还没下载你拍的影像
Well, I haven't even finished loading the images
从你的相机里
from your camera yet.
有关圆球的资料呢？
What about references to an orb?
我查过了
l took the liberty of checking.
月神殿的纪录中并没有圆球
Historical inventories of the Luna Temple do not list any orb.
那就查出希腊历史上出现过的所有圆球
Then I want you both to list every or ever mentioned in Greek history.
每一颗？
Every one?
那样的话…
That's…liable…
可能有…
to be…
好几千颗
…thousands.
好几千颗也要查
Then we'll read thousands.
先从那本书开始
Start with that one.
各位想来杯茶吗？
Perhaps you gentlemen would like some tea while you wait?
不用，茶是招待客人的
No, they wouldn't.Tea is for guests.
不速之客请出去
The door is for intruders.
劳拉 他们是英国情报局
Lara, these men are from Ml6.
他们西装毕挺，手无缚鸡之力
Yes, I can tell from their soft hands and pressed suits
一看就知道只会下令指使别人
that these are the men who make decisions and leave the dirty work for others.
我没兴趣… 他叫陈骆
l have no interest in… His name's Chen Lo.
他和弟弟陈宪
Along with his brother xien,
率领一帮土匪组成水灵帮
he runs a ring of Chinese bandits known as the Shay-Ling.
他们走私军火、钻石、古董，在黑市出售
They deal in guns, diamonds, antiquities, anything that Chen Lo can sell on the black market.
你一到希腊就被他们跟踪
They followed you from the moment you arrived in Santorini,
是他们杀了葛斯，沉了他的船
where they killed your friend, Gus, and sank his boat.
为什么？
Why?
为了这玩意儿
For this.
在你到达那以后
After you were picked up at sea,
我方在马尔他岛…拦截到这份传真
our listening post in Malta intercepted that fax.
是陈骆传给强纳森莱斯
It was sent from Chen Lo to a man named Jonathan Reiss.
那个赢得诺贝尔奖的科学家？
What, the scientist? Won the Nobel Prize.
他是全球顶尖的生化武器专家
He's now the foremost designer of biological weapons in the world.
他的创造是最核心的
His creations have been at the heart
十五年来，制造无数生化武器
of every act of bioterror in the past 15 years.
他无视人命，没有政治立场
Reiss's disdain for life is legendary. He has no political agenda.
不在乎他的武器杀死谁
He doesn't care who his weapons kill, or why.
他是现代的死亡天使
A modern-day Dr. Mengele.
我们知道陈骆跟踪你
We know Chen Lo followed you in order to obtain the orb,
抢走圆球卖给莱斯
but we also know that he'll deliver Reiss.
但是原因不明
What we don't know is why.
老实说，我们很害怕
Candidly, that terrifies us.
莱斯不是好惹的
Reiss is not to be trifled with.
潘朵拉魔盒
Pandora's box.
莱斯想用圆球找到潘朵拉魔盒
Reiss is going to use the orb to find Pandora's box.
那个希腊神话？
Do you mean the Greek myth?
潘朵拉打开禁忌魔盒
Pandora's given a box by God, told not to open it.
为全世界带来苦难？
She does and unleashes pain into the world?
那不只是神话
That's the Sunday school version, yes.
生命的起源是什么？
How do you think life began?
流星撞地球还是原始沼泽？
Shooting star, primordial ooze?
西元前2300年，埃及法老王
In 2300 BC, an Egyptian pharaoh
发现生命摇篮，那是人类生命的起源
found a place that he named the Cradle of Life, where we, life, began.
他在那儿发现一个盒子
And there, he found a box,
它为地球带来生命
the box which brought life to Earth.
当法老王打开盒子
The pharaoh opened the box,
里面只剩下代表死亡的洛曼提
but all that was left inside was the Ramante, or anti-life.
伴随生命而来的瘟疫
The plague which came as the companion to life
伴随而来？
Companion?
生命是一种平衡
Nature is about balance.
一切都有正反两面
All the world comes in pairs.
阴阳、善恶、男女
Yin and Yang.Right and wrong. Men and women.
难道就只有痛苦没有快乐吗？
What's pleasure without pain?
这场瘟疫造成什么？
What did this plague do?
它让法老王全军覆没
It leveled the pharaoh's army.
他儿子派出精兵
The pharaoh's son dispatched his finest soldier
将魔盒带到世界尽头
to take the box and transport it to the end of the world.
两千年后，亚历山大大帝来到印度
2, 000 years later, Alexander the Great reached India,
他的部下找到魔盒后，大军便被瘟疫毁灭
where his army was ravaged by a plague, after one of his men found a box among some remains.
印度？魔盒被带到印度？
India? That's where the pharaoh's man brought it?
亚历山大知道魔盒威力强大
Mmm. Alexander felt that the box was too powerful to be trusted to any man,
于是把它送回生命摇篮
so he returned it to its home in the Cradle of Life.
从此就消失无踪
And it has never been seen since.
生命摇篮在哪儿？
And this… Cradle of Life is where?
没有人知道
No one knows.
亚历山大用地图找到地方，
Alexander found it using a map that was with the box.
然后就藏起来
A map he then hid from the world.
但他为地图取名“马提”
But the name he gave this map was Mati.
照字面翻译的意思是眼睛
And the literal translation for the word "Mati" is "eye."
圆球就是地图
The orb is the map,
被亚历山大藏在月神殿
hidden in the Luna Temple by Alexander.
莱斯会用它找到潘朵拉魔盒
And Reiss will use it to find Pandora's box.
等他一打开它
And when he does, when he opens it,
就会释放超乎想像的强大武器
he will unleash a weapon more powerful than you could ever imagine.
这些刻痕构成图案
The markings definitely form a pattern, but…
就算我能解读
even if I figure out what they represent,
我们仍看不到整幅地图，因为…
we still can't read the whole map, because…
你只拍到一部分
we've only got a partial view of it, you see?
我们要设法解读它
Well, we have to figure out how to read it.
好，谢谢
Right. Thank you.
我代表女王陛下
On behalf of Her Majesty,
我们请你
we formally request that you find
赶在莱斯之前找到魔盒
and recover this box before Dr. Reiss.
哦
Oh!
既然女王陛下都开了金口
Well, now that I have Her Majesty's permission…
告诉我圆球在哪
Tell me where to find the orb.
它被陈骆带到中国
Last we heard, it was somewhere in China with Chen Lo and the Shay-Ling.
找到它们会很困难
Finding them will be next to impossible,
我会派两名顶尖情报员协助你
but we'll assign two of our best agents to help.
我不需要他们
l don't want them.
恕我直言，考古学家没法…
With all due respect, expertise in archaeology doesn't…
我没说我不需要帮忙
l didn't say that I don't need help,
但你们没法及时送我去中国
but your agents will never get me to Chen Lo in time.
我要熟悉对方的内线
l need an insider, someone who knows the Shay-Ling.
他们的手段和藏身处
Their methods, their hideouts.
我要泰瑞薛顿
l need Terry Sheridan.
就算全世界
Not in a million years.
只剩下他也不行
Not if he were the last man on Earth.
泰瑞薛顿，前皇家陆战队中校
Terry Sheridan, formerly a commander
后来成为佣兵和叛徒
with the Royal Marines, turned mercenary and traitor.
你让那傢伙拿到魔盒，
You don't honestly expect me to put that man on the trail of a weapon
他会卖给出价最高的人
he can turn around and sell to the highest bidder?
（哈萨克 巴拉卡拉监狱）
开门
Open.
我是典狱长阿敏卡尔
l am your host… Armin Kal.
欢迎光临奇幻岛
Welcome to Fantasy lsland.
卡芙特
Croft.
你好，泰瑞
Hello, Terry.
你觉得我的新家怎样？
So, what do you think of my new place?
当然比不上你的豪宅
It's not quite Croft Manor.
这是你心扉的钥匙？
What? A key to your heart?
苏黎世公寓的
To a flat in Zurich.
你可以挑另一座城市
You can pick another city, if you want.
你的纪录会一笔勾销
Your record will be expunged
并恢复你的身分
your citizenship restored.
谁？
By?
英国情报局
Ml6.
这算浮士德的魔鬼交易吗？
Now, would that make me Faust…or the Devil?
随便你，他们会替你安排新身分
Well, you can pick one, because Ml6 will also arrange a new identity.
是吗？我不需要他们帮忙
Oh, yeah?You think I need their help?
口是心非方面除外
Oh, having two faces doesn't count.
我为此要做些什么？
So, what do I have to do?
带我去找水灵帮
You need to take me to the Shay-Ling.
水灵帮？
The Shay who?
陈骆抢走我的东西
There's a man named Chen Lo
我要拿回来
who took something from me, and I want it back.
不是情报局吗？不关我的事
Yeah, now, is that you or Ml6?
事成之后
Also, I've arranged for the government
你有五百万镑
to wire you five million in sterling when we succeed.
就算是你的买命钱
You can call it second-chance money.
或是你的保险
Or life insurance, for you.
我不需要
l don't need any.
我们独自行动？
You and l, working alone?
这样比较容易看透你
Well, it's easier to see through you that way.
然后呢？
So, what if afterwards,
要是情报局后悔放我出去呢？
Ml6 decides that me back in the world isn't such a great idea?
他们派谁抓你，我都为他难过
Then I feel sorry for whomever they get to come after you.
他们授权你杀我？
Do you have authorization to kill me, Croft?
随时随地，任何理由
Anytime, for any reason.
那你为何不动手？
So, why don't you just do it, then?
是不是女性的满腔怒火？
What is it they say? "Hell hath no fury."
你没那么行
You're not that good.
水灵帮神出鬼没，劳拉
The Shay-Ling are like ghosts, Croft.
他们不停移动
They move constantly,
躲在中国最偏远的山区
and their home is the most remote mountain region in China.
山区？
Region?
你要更有把握
You'll have to do better than that.
只要送我进中国
Get me into China,
一天内我就能找到他们
and I'll get you to them in a day.
不准用枪、金钱或任何武器
No guns, no money, no weapons of any kind.
那岂不是人生无趣
Talk about taking the fun out of life.
中国到处有他们的眼线
The Shay-Ling have spies all over China.
我们要偷渡到北京
We have to get into the country undetected.
然后坐卡车
So, we slip into Beijing, and we go by truck.
卡车？
Truck? Hmm.
我想的是更快的交通工具
l was thinking about something a little faster.
更快一点？
A little faster?
这玩意是很快，
Well, this is a little faster,
不过中国军方会发现
but the Chinese will track the pod.
不会留下东西被发现
There won't be any pod to find.
那我们会尸骨无存吗？
Will there be any of us to find?
准备好了没
Ready? Now.
准备什么？
Ready for what?
这一招挺炫的，劳拉
The ditching was good, Croft.
我很佩服
I'll give you that.
不过这鬼地方绝对找不到车子
But we're never going to find a vehicle in a place like this.
真高兴见到你
Oh, it's so lovely to see you.
都准备好了吗？
So, is everything ready?
是的
Yes.
你的衣服、枪和刀子在那儿
Your clothes, guns and knives are over there.
我顺便替你修好了机车
And I took the liberty of tuning your bike.
- 可以吗？ - 请便
- May I? - Yes.
我是劳拉
Lara.
你们小俩口在干嘛？
Ah, what is the happy couple up to?
整装待发
Accessorizing.
圆球解读得怎样？
Where are we on reading the orb?
每份地图都有解说
All maps have a key, Lara, a scale, a legend, yes?
它不在圆球上
The orb's key, it's not on the orb.
一定遗失了
It must've been lost.
或者在月神殿
Or is somewhere in the temple.
仔细看我在圆球附近拍的照片
Go through every image I took.Start with the ones near the orb.
解说一定跟圆球有关
The key must have been linked to it in some way.
好了，再见
Right.Bye, then.
劳拉通常都没有搭档
It's unlike Lara to take a partner.
你们要去哪？
Where are you two going?
我们要去远足
We'll take a nice little trip.
到山区呼吸新鲜空气
Breathe some fresh mountain air.
顺便看看水灵帮的老朋友
Stop by my friends, the Shay-Ling.
水灵帮守住每条路
The Shay-Ling watch all the roads.
我们从后面绕道
We'll have to go around the back.
我们直捣黄龙
We'll go straight.
也许你没听见我说的
Maybe you didn't hear me.
从这儿到洛阳
The Shay-Ling have men on every road
每条路都有他们的人
from here to Lo Yang.
不是每条路
Not every road.
你变逊了
A bit rusty, are we?
感觉回来了
Oh, I think it's coming back.
苏格兰男人都这么逊？
l expected more from a Scot.
我对英国女人才没兴趣
l don't expect anything from an Englishwoman.
很好，因为你也别想占便宜
Good, 'cause you're not going to get anything.
没得玩了
Fun's over.
现在要用走的
From now on, it's by foot.
你最好再考虑让我拿枪
Best to reconsider that "no gun" rule.
免谈
No.
好吧
Okay.
别盯着我的屁股看
And don't be looking at my ass.
我是什么角色？
So, where do I fit in?
你是向导
What do you mean? You're the guide.
我是说…
l mean, when you think back
在你多采多姿的冒险生活
on the vast scheme of your hugely adventurous life…
我扮演的是什么角色？
where do I fit in?
我是你的情人或者绊脚石？
Was I the love of your life, or just another bump on the road?
你跟我在一起的四个月
Was I time well spent?Four months?
应该很快乐吧？
More good than bad?
不只是这样吧？
Come on, it had to be more than that, am I right?
你说得对
You're right.
我们在一起有五个月
It was five months.
- 你在笑我 - 没有
- You're laughing at me. - No, no.
因为我以前觉得你很迷人
At the fact, l used to find you charming.
我还是很迷人
l am charming.
嗯
Hmm.
你迟到了
You're late.
头向后仰，快
Tilt your head back. Do it!
一小时后就看得见了
You might see again in an hour. Maybe.
搞什么？它不在里面
What's this?It's not there.
没有圆球
There's no orb.
你知道些什么吗？
ls there anything you can tell me about this?
哪位
Hello.
你不喜欢你的信差？
l take it you didn't like your messenger.
没错
l didn't.
但我比较喜欢在月神殿死掉的
But I did like the men I lost in the temple.
你低估了卡芙特女士
You underestimated Lady Croft.
我低估了这颗圆球的价值
l underestimated how much this orb is worth.
世上有这么多可怕的疾病
There's so many horrible diseases in the world…
小孩子最容易受到传染
things we are particularly susceptible to as children.
也许哪天你抱着你的心肝宝贝
You never know when you could be holding little Shiho or Tai by the hand
他们突然就染上怪病暴毙了
as a mysterious ailment ravages their bodies.
你敢杀了他们，我就把圆球交给卡芙特
You kill them, and I will give your orb to Lady Croft.
我手下说她目前离这儿很近
My men tell me she is a few miles away from here, as we speak.
不知道她肯出多少钱
l wonder how much she would pay.
我愿意多付一千两百万
I'll pay you an additional 12 million dollars.
只要你交出圆球和她的尸体，钱就是你的了
It will be yours, once you've delivered the orb to me, along with Lady Croft's body.
你不知道他们的下落
l don't think you know where they are.
你好烦
You're impossible, you know that?
你假装知道，好骗我带你出狱
l think you pretended to know, so I would get you out.
这不是古墓，劳拉
This isn't a tomb, Croft,
水灵帮不是木乃伊
and the Shay-Ling aren't mummies.
他们杀人不眨眼
They're killers.
如果你不信任我…
But if you don't trust me…
我很抱歉要这么做，但你在浪费时间
I'm sorry to have to do this, but you're wasting time.
你想杀我就动手吧
You want to shoot me? Shoot me.
我宁可你动手
Personally, I'd rather you do it…
也不愿落在他们手中
than them.
泰瑞
Well, Terry…
我不是叫你别再回来吗？
What part of "Never come back again", didn't you understand?
你想找到水灵帮
You wanted to find the Shay-Ling.
快走
Come on!
唯一的方法就是当他们的俘虏
The only way to get into their place is as their prisoners.
你干嘛不早说
Ah, you might have told me that little gem before.
你会相信吗？
Ah, you would have believed me?
只要你出高价
Make Chen Lo a better offer than his buyer.
陈骆就会背叛买主
He'll cross them.
就算买主是强纳森莱斯？
Even if his buyer is Jonathan Reiss?
你也早该告诉我
You might have told me that little gem before.
你真的会杀我吗？
Were you really going to kill me?
我敢说她一定会
Oh, I bet she would have.
我见识过
l have seen her in action.
泰瑞没告诉你吗？
Didn't Terry tell you?
上次我们见到他，他开着一辆卡车
The last time any of us saw him, he was riding away with a truck
载着一卡车从我这里偷走的明朝花瓶
full of my Ming vases.
坐在他旁边的…
And sitting next to him…
是他的妹子
was his sister.
她还好吗？
Well, how is she?
你…不该来的
You… shouldn't have come here.
至少我能出狱
It got me out of prison.
何况她出的价钱很高
Besides, the lady has a good offer.
比莱斯还高
Better than Reiss.
是吗？
Really?
我该接受吗？
Should I take it?
接受吧
Take it.
或者我们拿她和东西向英国政府要三倍价钱
Or, better yet, you and I ransom her and the thing back to the British for triple.
咱们谈谈
Let's talk.
不是你，泰瑞
Not you, Terry.
是卡芙特女士
Lady Croft and l.
你留下来，跟他叙叙旧吧
You wait here.Catch up.
我四分钟就回来
I'll be four minutes.
太好了
Terrific.
你一定会喜欢这些
There's something I think you will appreciate.
这是我发现最大一批兵马俑
This is the largest groupof terra-cotta warriors I have found.
秦始皇建造它们供死后使用
The King of Chin made them for use in the afterlife…
替他击退阴间的敌人
to fend off enemies he made in this one.
听起来我们都用得着
Hmm. Sounds like we could both use a set.
我很乐意卖一些给你
l would be happy to sell some to you.
我希望你也肯把圆球卖给我
l hope you're as entrepreneurial with the orb.
我们都失去手下
You lost men, I lost men.
没理由再损兵折将
l see no reason we should both lose again.
如果我要莱斯出的两倍价钱…
If I want double what Reiss offered me?
东西在你手上？
Is it here?
它很值钱
It's worth a lot.
你该知道莱斯拿到货会杀了你
Well, then, if you know that, you know Reiss will also kill you the moment you give it to him.
你的政府会保护我吗？
And your government will guarantee my safety?
不会
No.
但是我会保护你
But I will.
你这么说一定很不情愿
That must hurt, saying that to me.
接受我的条件
Take the offer.
你是在命令我？
You presume to give me orders?
趁现在就接受我的条件
Take the offer, before it expires.
不要
No.
那我只好强迫你
Then I will have to force you.
那我只好杀了你
Then I will have to kill you.
噢
Oh…
四分钟到了吗？
Has it been four minutes yet?
真爽
That was nice.
很可惜你站错边了
It's too bad you're on the wrong side.
说出圆球下落，我就饶你一命
Tell me where the orb is, and it spares your life.
法华塔，上海
The flower pagoda, in Shanghai.
晚上九点整
9:00 p.m.
这是我的
This is mine.
咱们扯平了
Now we're even.
动手
Now!
还记得不准用枪吗？
Remember that "no gun" rule?
我改变主意
l reconsidered!
你知道有阶梯可以走吧？
l know there's a staircase we could've used.
劳拉，你还好吧？
Lara, are you all right?
好得很
Smashing.
我要去上海
I'm on my way to Shanghai,
帮我看样东西
and I need you to look at something for me.
这是在月神殿找到的
It was in the Luna Temple near the orb.
我打赌一定是地图之钥
And I'm betting it's the key to those markings.
她拿着某种乐器
She's holding some sort of musical instrument.
是声音
It's sound.
太高明了
That's brilliant.
这一定有关联
The key must have been linked to it in some way.
我开始解读影像
I'll start decoding the images we have
很好
Good.
你搞定其余的部分 再见 劳拉
You get us the rest.Bye, Lara.
- 想你 - 再见
- Miss you. - Bye.
（上海）
（法华塔 8点50分）
你看
Oh, well.
就像从前一样
Just like old times.
这是你第一次…
l think that's the first time
因为我露出笑容
you've actually smiled because of me.
你为何那么做？
Why did you do it?
我想通了
l started thinking.
我不想再替别人做事
l was tired of doing things somebody else's way,
我老是替别人卖命
and it was always going to be somebody else's way.
所以你就出卖同胞和国家？
So, you abandon your men and betray your country?
离开我的同胞和国家
Leaving my men and my country,
比我想像的容易
that didn't actually hurt as much as I thought.
离开你才痛苦
But leaving you did.
嗯
Mm.
没有人比得上你，劳拉
You're a hard act to follow, Croft.
你知道我们为何这么配吗？
You know why you and I get along so well?
不知道
No.
我们是天生一对，你和我
We are two of a kind, me and you.
我跟你完全不同
We are nothing alike.
我不是说我们很像
l don't think we're alike,
但我认为我们是最佳拍档
but I do think we're a pair.
就像铜板的正反面
Opposite sides of the same coin.
我的人守住屋顶
My men have the roof covered.
你降落在广场
Why don't you set down in the square instead?
我的手下也能守住四周
That way, my men will also have things covered.
好吧
Okay, fine.
西恩，上吧
Okay, Sean, let's go!
他们要降落在广场
They're landing in the square.
我们位置不对
We're in the wrong position.
走楼梯？
Stairs?
来不及了
No time.
- 从屋顶？ - 不行
- Rooftops? - No.
我有个主意
I've got a plan.
你留在这
Stay here.
等我的信号
Wait for my signal.
钱在这儿
Here's the money!
快来拿
Come and get it!
不是要等我的信号吗？
Wait for my signal, huh?
箱子给我
Give me that box!
先把钱给我 快！
You give me my money first!Come on!
现在就给我箱子
Give me that box now!
不，先给钱
No, just toss it.
你先给！
You first!
我的天，快走
Quick! Get us out of here!
快升空
Take us up!
快飞上去
Take it up!
快，撞死她
Go! Run her over!
干嘛？
Yeah?
我不想以你的方式
We tried it your way.
现在该照我的方式了
Now we do it mine!
把东西带到塔顶
Bring it to the top of the pagoda now!
好吧
Okay!
我抓住你了
l got you!
快，拿过来
Come on! Come on! Hold it up!
靠近点
Come closer!l can't reach it!
举高一点
Raise it higher!Higher!
向你老哥致意
My regards to your brother!
来不及了
We're too late.
劳拉，你在干嘛？
Croft, what are you doing?
飞上去
Take us up!
快点
Move! Go!
走人，开车
Let's go! Move!
拜托别再拿枪指着我
I'm getting tired of you pointing that thing at me.
你还好吧？
Are you okay?
好得很
Never better.
看来圆球搞丢了
Looks like we lost the orb.
我跳那么高可不是白忙一场
Please. You don't think I'd go vaulting into thin air for nothing, do you?
我在箱子上放了追踪器
l put a tracer on the crate.
（罗盘）
找到了，你看
Got it. Look.
（上海-香港）
佩服
Impressive.
（香港）
市中心有武器实验室？不可能的事
A weapons lab in the middle of the city? No way.
他一定把箱子丢了
He must've dumped that crate.
不，圆球在这儿
No, it's here.
在这些大楼里面？
One of the buildings?
不对，就在我们站的地方
No. It's exactly where we're standing.
我以为潘朵拉魔盒只是神话
There's a part of me that always allowed for the possibility that Pandora's box was just a legend,
但是我现在知道它是真的
but now I know it's there.
她逃走了
She escaped.
她不知道我们的下落
She has no idea where we are.
我们不能冒险
We take no chances.
把所有制造解毒剂的装备都装上喷射机
Have everything we need to manufacture an antidote transferred to the jet.
（48%解读完成）
我要你安排两个人逃生
l need an out for two people.
市中心，动作快点
Mid-city. Soon.
你疯了？
What, are you crazy?
安排好了？
Are we set?
小意思
Piece of cake.
你好
Hello.
太容易了
So much for easy.
那是什么？
What is that?
他已经开始解读圆球
He's already decoding the orb.
可恶
Bugger.
拿对讲机
Headset.
（危险生化物）
你得设法让大家出去
You've got to get everyone out.
有什么好主意，消防警铃？
What do you suggest, the fire alarm?
不赖嘛
Not bad.
只是警铃响而已
But that's just the alarm.
又没有危险
There's no danger.
你认为他们敢不要命吗？
Do you think anyone here is paid enough to take that chance?
想都别想
Don't even think about it.
是她
It's her.
怎么了？
Yes?
该死
Damn!
我很高兴，劳拉
I'm glad, Lara.
要杀你太容易了
That would've been too easy.
露两手来看看
Give me your best.
这招怎样？
How's that?
（94%解读完成）
我要切断通讯了
I'm going off-line.
等一下
No, don't…
谢谢
Thanks.
不客气
You're welcome.
你们好 伙计们
Hello, boys.
弄清楚金牌的图案了吗
Did you understand the medallion?
对
Yeah. Yeah.
那些刻痕是声波
The, uh, the markings are sound waves.
我们已解读出半颗圆球的部分
We've translated all the markings from your images roughly half the orb.
现在就搞定它
Well, let's complete the set then.
我录好剩余的部分
I'll record the rest of the images
然后传给你
and send them to you.
你解读好了
Once you have them, finish the translation
就把声音回传给我
and transmit the sounds back to me.
我们要更多人手
We need more backup.
真聪明
Smart girl.
（95%解读完成）
走开
Move.
别杀她
Don't shoot her.
先等电脑完成解读
Not until we're sure the computer has done its job.
你真以为
Do you honestly believe you'll be able
能控制魔盒
to control what's in that box
把它变成武器？
and turn it into another one of your weapons?
劳拉，你真让我失望
Really, Lara, you disappoint me.
买家的钱都收齐了吗？
Have we received payment from all the buyers?
没有
No…
你根本不想控制它
you don't want to control it at all.
你只是利用买家
You're using the buyers.
让他们当成武器释放它
They'll release it, thinking it's just another weapon
那全世界都会责怪他们
and the world blames them.
是世界上仅存的人类责怪他们
What's left of the world blames them.
等我拿到病毒
Once I've got hold of the virus,
我就会制造解毒剂
I'll make enough antidote
保护精英分子
to protect the best and the brightest.
企业大亨、国家元首，生命还是会延续下去
Heads of corporations.Heads of state.Life will go on.
别说你没想过
Don't tell me you've never looked around and thought,
凡夫俗子死光了，该有多好
"Wouldn't the world be a better place without some of these people?"
我倒觉得，你死了最好
Well, I can certainly think of one person I could do without.
（解读完成）
终于好了
There it is.
对不起，劳拉
I'm sorry, Lara.
我本来想欢迎你来我的世界
You would've been welcome in my world.
去死吧
Piss off.
一枪宰了她
Shoot her between the eyes.
别失手
No mistakes.
混帐
You asshole!
我要宰了你
I'm going to get you!
跟我来
Follow me!
你死定了
You're mine.
太棒了
Bingo.
两张离开香港的单程票
Two one-way tickets out of Hong Kong.
降落伞
Parachutes.
这玩意儿更快
Something a little faster.
快点
Come on!
会合点在两里半，或许三里外
Our rendezvous point is two and a half, maybe three miles.
你明知没人跳伞能超过一里
You're aware that no one's ever gone further than one mile.
这玩意儿就行
l am now.
在这儿
This way!
你先跳
Right, you go first.
不，你先跳
No, you go first.
我先跳好了
I'll go first!
我的天
Holy cow.
跟着她
Follow her.
泰瑞，很高兴见到你
My friend!Good to see you.
你要我付钱，对吧？
l suppose you want pay now, don't you?
我们说好两百美元
So what did we agree on, $200?
不，三百块
No, 300.
这么说…
So this…
这颗圆球是地图？
…rock is the map?
没错
Yes, it is.
我没见过这种东西，你呢？
I've never seen anything like it, have you?
只能靠它找到潘朵拉魔盒？
And it's the only way to find that box?
你大可以把它抢了
And just think, you could take it now
就夺门而出
and walk right out the door.
不，跳窗更快
No, window's better actually. Off the ship faster.
你追不到
Harder to track.
劳拉，你真以为我会这么做？
Oh, Croft, do you really think I would do that to you?
你可以扭断我的手腕
You can break my wrist,
但我还是要亲你
but I'm still going to kiss you.
啊？
Huh?
这不是我心里想的，不过也好
Well, not exactly what I had in mind, but okay.
你为何不杀了莱斯？
Why didn't you shoot Reiss?
什么？
What?
他在实验室一定有经过你面前
He must have walked right past you in the lab.
你为何不开枪？
Why didn't you shoot him?
我没把握
l didn't have a clear shot
我也不知你在哪儿
and I had no idea where you were.
我会通知情报局说你完成任务
I'll inform Ml6 of the completion of your service.
你会拿到钱和新身分
You'll have your money and your life.
别浪费了
Don't waste it.
妈的 劳拉
Damn it, Croft,
你不能就这样走人
this is no time to split up.
当然可以，在你走错路之前
Yes, it is, before you make the wrong decision.
好，你想走就走吧
Okay, you want to leave?
走吧
Go ahead.
别假装这是救我一命
But don't pretend it's to try and save me.
你害怕
You're afraid.
你害怕你不忍心下手
Afraid you might not pull the trigger.
你也害怕让别人进入你的心扉
Afraid of letting your guard down, of letting anyone in.
我不是不忍心下手才要走
I'm not leaving because I couldn't kill you.
我是因为我敢下手才离开
I'm leaving because I could.
啊？
Huh?
早上好
我能不能借用你们的电视机
这很重要
干杯
Cheers.
太好了
Lovely.
布莱斯
Hello, Bryce.
劳拉
Hello, Lara.
准备好了吗？
Are you ready?
好了
Yeah.
好，圆球剩余的影像…
Right. Sending the last images of the orb…
传送中
now
收到了
Got them.
解读中…
Translating.
完成
Done.
传送声音
Send the sounds.
传送中
Sending it now.
没反应
No, nothing.
又要重新解读了
Oh, well, back to the drawing board.
等等，声波失真了
No, wait.The tones are being distorted.
把档案传送给我
Send me the file.
劳拉，我觉得不会成功的
Look, Lara, l…l really don't think that's gonna work, you know?
一定会成功
Yes, course it will.
这就跟听自己的录音一样
Ever heard your voice on a tape recorder?
一样的
Same thing.
我干嘛跟你说这么多
Why are we having this discussion?
档案传过来就对了
Send me the file.
传送中
Senging it.
谢谢
Thank you.
劳拉
Lara?
地点在非洲
Africa. It's in Africa.
靠近吉力马扎罗山
Somewhere near Kilimanjaro.
太好了，劳拉
Great, Lara.
莱斯要多久才能修好电脑？
How long will it take Reiss to put his computers back together?
最快也要24小时
24 hours at the fastest.
联络库萨
Get in touch with Kosa.
请他开车在村落北方接我
Ask him to get the car and meet me north of his village,
八点整
0800 hours.
再见
Bye, then.
我们用不着24小时
A bit faster than 24 hours, I'd say.
出去
Out.
那就去非洲吧
Africa it is.
- 库萨　 - 劳拉
- Kosa - Lara!
你好吗？
How are you?
劳拉？
Lara?
你把吉普车洗干净了
You had the jeep cleaned.
当然
Of course.
我知道你爱惜装备
I know how you like your equipment.
你在哪？我看不到你
Where are you? I can't see you.
放心，我看得到你
Don't worry. I can see you.
你会从哪个方向过来？
Okay, where are you coming from now?
继续向前开
Keep going straight.
保持车速
Keep your speed steady.
劳拉，欢迎回来
Lara, welcome back!
你每次都要搞这么复杂吗？
Do you ever do anything the easy way?
我不想让你失望
And risk disappointing you?
我丢失了一个朋友，不知道哪里去找
衣服很漂亮
你好，她去非洲和大象一起玩
库萨，我们没来过这儿
Kosa, we've never been here, have we?
我们是没来过，为什么？
We didn't come to this area before. Why?
我见过那座山
Because I've seen that mountain before.
潘朵拉魔盒就在那儿
The box is there somewhere.
原住民都叫它“神之圣山”
The locals call it "The Mountain of God."
那儿有一个部落或许能帮你
There's a tribethat makes their home on it that might help us.
东西留下来就走吧
Leave this object and go.
东西留下就快走
Leave this object and go!
别再提起这件事
Never speak of it.
擅自闯入生命摇篮
To trespass on the Cradle of Life
将为全世界带来
is to risk flooding the entire world
死亡
with death.
有人要来抢魔盒
Men are coming for the box
他们不像我对它心存敬畏
and unlike me, they won't look at it with fear, or respect.
他们会打开魔盒，把它当作武器
They will open it. They want to use it.
很抱歉要打扰你们的神明
And I'm sorry if I have to disturb your gods
我要阻止这件事
to keep this from happening…
但是我一定要这么做
but I will do whatever I must.
你真的明白你在做什么？
Do you truly understand what you are doing?
你能接受你将见到的事实吗？
Are you truly prepared for what you're about to learn?
有些秘密不该泄漏
Some secrets must remain secrets.
这是一个沉重孤独的负担
These are very heavy burdens, very lonely burdens.
如果你找到魔盒，就要背负重担
And if you find the box, you will have to carry them.
我准备好了
l am prepared, sir.
他说来找魔盒的人都一去不返
He warns that no one who has gone looking for the box has come back.
他说峡谷另一端有黑影护卫
He says the land beyond the canyon belongs to the Shadow Guardians.
黑影护卫？
Shadow Guardians?
它们不睡觉
They do not sleep.
永远不休息
They never rest.
像疾风一样快速
They move like a wind.
闯入禁地者必死无疑
And anything that walks their land, will die.
生命摇篮呢？
And the Cradle itself?
只有圆球能让它显现
Only with the orb can it be revealed.
那儿是一个颠倒世界
Inside you will find a place of madness…
天地混合为一
sky and earth are one,
方向感也毫无意义
direction meaningless.
他要派二十人带领我们
He's going to give us 20 men to take us as far as they can…
深入魔盒所在的生命摇篮
to the Cradle of Life, where the box is hidden.
我们越来越近了
We're getting closer.
他说你没说错
He said you are right.
生命摇篮就在山峰附近
The Cradle of Life lies near the summit.
他问你怎么会知道
He wants to know how you knew.
那颗圆球
The orb.
他说他不会跟别人回去
He says he will not turn back with the others.
他要陪我们一起去
He will go as far as we go.
他要对抗黑影护卫
He will fight the Shadow Guardians.
你很勇敢
You're a very brave man.
他说什么？
What is… what is he saying?
你的腔调很可笑
That your accent is funny.
趴下
Get down!
快趴下
回去
Back! Back!
快退回去
Back! Get back!
谢谢你劳拉带我们
Thank you, Lara, for leading us here,
来这儿和找到圆球
and for finding the orb in the first place.
不过你看过正确位置
However, you have seen the exact position.
可以替我们节省很多时间
You could save me hours, days even.
你只要帮我就会有好处
Help me; I'll make it worth your while.
免谈
No.
你好好考虑一下
But think of what I'm offering you.
放开她
Let her go.
目睹一切开端的好机会
The chance to find out how it all began.
人类的生命起源
Life, Lara, the origin of what we are.
别说你不想知道
Don't tell me you're not tempted.
潘朵拉就是这样惹出麻烦
That's what got Pandora into trouble.
他们说你不会从命
They told me you wouldn't do it,
我却说你一定不想失去挚友
and I told them you would rather than lose two of your closest friends.
带我们去生命摇篮
Take us to the Cradle of Life.
对不起，劳拉
I'm sorry, Lara.
去那儿是你的使命
It's your destiny to see what's inside.
没错
He is right.
它就在峡谷另一头，记得吗？
It's just beyond the canyon, remember?
走几步路就能救你朋友一命
Such a short walk might save your friends.
如果能救我朋友
Well, if it spares my friends…
那我就愿意去
I'm up for a walk.
我相信她一定能体谅
I'm sure she'd understand!
我有个计划
l have a plan.
你早该警告她我们是人质
You should have just told Lara we were hostage.
莱斯就不会找到她
Reiss would never have found out!
你们应该不会开直升机吧？
l don't suppose either of you know how to fly a helicopter?
我会
l can.
- 真的吗？ - 什么？
- What? - What?
我飞模拟电玩和遥控模型，超过150小时
Yeah. I've got over 150 hours between flight simulation games, models.
真正的经验呢？
And in the real thing?
- 两小时　 - 两小时？
- Two. - Two?
你只要飞一次
Well, you're only going to fly it once I'm out,
希望你还记得怎么飞
so I hope you remember your two hours well.
- 通过这儿？ - 嗯.
- It's through here? - Mm.
走吧，宝贝
Move, baby.
那是怎么回事？
What was that?
你们去查一下
You! Check it out!
继续走
Keep moving.
你们在干嘛？快回队伍
What are you doing? Back in formation, now!
我的天
Holy shit!
别动，它们好像对动作有反应
Don't! They seem to react to movement.
它们走了
They're gone.
就快到了
l know we're close.
我看得出来
I've seen it in your eyes.
带我找到潘朵拉魔盒
Take me to Pandora's box.
我不知道怎么找
l don't know how.
快去
Do it now!
是你说你想走几步路
Well, you were the one who wanted to go for a walk,
快走啊
so start walking.
下一枪就是朝你身上开
The next one will be higher.
只有圆球能让它显现
Only with the orb can it be revealed.
我去
All right.
圆球给我
I'll need the orb.
你到底想不想看生命摇篮？
Do you want to see the Cradle of Life or not?
你跟我说该怎么做
You tell me what to do with it.
嗨！
Hey!
你别想耍我，劳拉
Don't think you can outwit me, Croft.
闭嘴
Oh, do shut up.
原来这就是生命摇篮
So, this is the Cradle of Life.
我们到了
Here we are.
交给你了
She's all yours.
该英雄救美了
Time to be a hero.
在那儿
There it is.
太完美了，对吧？
Perfect, isn't it?
不起眼的盒子却拥有强大力量
All that power in such a banal container.
传说当潘朵拉看见魔盒内部…
Legend tells that when Pandora saw inside the box,
就流下一池黑色硫酸眼泪
she cried a pool of black acid for tears.
既然是女人发现魔盒
And as it was a woman who found the box,
我想没有理由打破优良传统
l see no reason to break with tradition.
应该是女人去拿魔盒
A woman should collect the box.
快去拿
Go on!
我够不到
It is impossible to reach.
快拿
Now, take it!
快拿上来
Take it!
你想都别想，莱斯
l don't think so, Reiss!
你没事吧？
You okay?
哇
Whoa.
我没事
I'm fine. I'm fine.
坐下吧
There you go.
好
Right.
你是有备而来
You come prepared.
我知道你笨手笨脚
Well, I know how clumsy you are.
希拉瑞和布莱斯呢？
Hillary and Bryce?
他们没事
They're fine.
谢了
Thank you.
你说什么？
What was that?
哦…
Oh…
谢谢你
thank you.
我们走吧
Let's get out of here.
泰瑞
Terry?
你在干嘛？
What are you doing?
你开玩笑吧？
What? You're joking, right?
这是我们的，我要把它带走
We're taking this with us.This is ours.
你不能把魔盒带走
You're not walking out of here with that box.
你在说什么？
So, what are you saying?
这么值钱的东西要留在这儿？
We just leave it, when it's worth a fortune?
放回去
Put it back.
办不到
No, I don't think so.
它会害死成千上万的无辜百姓
It could kill millions of innocent people.
你太大惊小怪了
Now you're being dramatic.
放回去
Put it back.
不
No!
我帮你阻止莱斯的阴谋
I've helped you keep this away from Reiss.
这是我的奖赏
This is my reward.
我要把它带走
I'm taking it with me.
终究要翻脸，是吧？
So, it's come to this, has it?
你是有权杀死我
Well, you do have authorization to kill me.
最好赶快动手
Better do it, then.
如果你以为
Cause if you think
站在我前面就能拦住我
standing in front of me is going to be enough…
你没有那个能耐
You don't have it in you to stop me.
你的一切信念…
See, all your beliefs…
你的理想
all your ideals…
都不是真的
they're not real.
我才真实
l am.
你也爱我
And you've loved me.
我不知你自以为有多强悍
l don't know how strong you think you are,
但你绝不会为了那些而杀我
but you are not going to choose them over me.
让开
Now move.
不
No
好吧
Fine.
魔盒安全了
The box is safe now.
有些东西不该被找到
Some things are not meant to be found.
你每次都要搞这么复杂吗？
Can't you ever do anything the easy way?
我可不想让你失望
l wouldn't want to disappoint you.
劳拉，你没事吧？
Lara, are you okay?
劳拉，你还好吧？
Lara, you all right?
你们…好感人哦
This is… very touching.
你也知道我们最爱交朋友…
You know us, always making friends…
四处寻开心
having a laugh.
还有结婚
Getting married.
什么？
What?
这是婚礼，你们是新郞
This is a wedding ceremony and you are the grooms.
祝你们幸福
Good luck, boys.
快闪！
Go!